This next lecture is my absolute favorite lecture in introduction to deep learning,
这一节课是我绝对最喜欢的深度学习入门课程，
focusing on the limitations of deep learning methods as they exist today,
重点讲述当今深度学习方法的局限性，
and how those limitations and outstanding challenges really motivate
以及这些局限性和突出挑战如何真正激励
new research at the cutting edge and the new frontiers of deep learning and AI.
深度学习和人工智能前沿和新领域的新研究。
Before we dive in,
在我们开始之前，
we have a couple of logistical things to to discuss and go through,
我们有几件[后勤]方面的事情要讨论，
starting with perhaps one of the most important aspects of this of this course,
首先可能是本课程中最重要的方面之一，
we have a tradition of designing and giving T-shirts
我们有设计和赠送 T恤的传统，
as part of this course
作为课程的一部分，
and hopefully you can all see them,
希望你们都能看到，
we have them here today right at the front.
今天它们就在这里，就在前面，
So we're going to do the distribution of the T-shirts at the end of today's program,
所以我们将在今天的编程结束时分发 T恤，
and so please, please stay if you wish to pick up a T-shirt.
所以，请留下来，如果你想要一件 T恤。
All right, so where we are right now,
好的，所以在我们现在的位置，
we have this lecture,
我们有一节课，
that I'm going to be giving on deep learning limitations and new frontiers,
我要讲的是深度学习的局限性和新的领域，
and we're going to have three more lectures following that,
在那之后我们还会有三场讲座，
continuing our series of guest lectures for this year.
继续我们今年的客座讲座系列。
Importantly, we still have the competitions surrounding both the software lab and the project pitch proposal,
重要的是，我们仍然有围绕软件实验和项目推介提案的竞争，
for the project pitch proposal,
对于项目推介提案，
we ask that you please upload your slides by tonight,
我们要求你在今晚之前上传幻灯片，
we have all the detailed instructions for that on the course syllabus,
我们在课程大纲上有关于这方面的所有详细说明，
and if you are interested in submitting to the lab competitions,
如果你有兴趣提交实验竞赛，
the deadline for that has been extended to tomorrow afternoon at 1pm,
截止日期已经延长到明天下午 1 点，
so please submit the labs, for the labs as well.
因此，请同时提交实验。
Motivation hopefully is not only to is mostly to exercise your skills in deep learning and to build knowledge,
希望动机不仅仅是锻炼你在深度学习中的技能和积累知识，
but we also have these amazing competitions and prizes
而且我们还有这些令人惊叹的比赛和奖品，
for each of the labs as well as the project pitch proposal competition.
对于每个实验以及项目推介比赛。
So to remind you for the first lab on designing neural networks for music generation,
为了提醒你第一个关于设计神经网络以产生音乐的实验，
we have audio related prizes that are up up in the air,
我们有与音频相关的奖项悬而未决，
the competition is wide open,
比赛是公开的，
can be anyone's game,
可以是任何人的比赛，
so please please, please submit your entries.
所以请提交你们的参赛作品。
Tomorrow we'll have the project pitch proposal competition,
明天我们将举行项目推介大赛，
every year it's a highlight of this program,
每年它都是这个节目的一个亮点，
we hear your amazing ideas about new deep learning algorithms applications
我们听到了你关于新的深度学习算法应用程序的惊人想法，
in a quick shark tank style,
一种快速的[鲨鱼缸]风格，
Three minute pitch is really fun,
三分钟的演讲真的很有趣，
not only to be up here and have the chance to present to everyone,
不仅能站在这里，有机会向大家展示，
but also to hear the amazing ideas of your coursemates and your peers and colleagues,
还能听到你的同学、同事们令人惊叹的想法，
again, some of the logistical information for how to submit your slides up to the Google slide deck are included on the syllabus.
同样，一些关于如何将幻灯片提交到谷歌幻灯片卡片组的后勤信息也包括在教学大纲中。
And finally, as we introduced in the first lecture,
最后，正如我们在第一节课中介绍的，
and hopefully you've realized,
希望你们已经意识到，
we have an exciting grand prize competition
我们有一个令人兴奋的大奖竞赛，
surrounding the lab on trustworthy, deep learning, robustness, uncertainty and bias,
围绕着实验室的可信性、深度学习、稳健性、不确定性和偏见，
and again, emphasizing the competition is wide open right now,
再次强调，竞争现在是完全开放的，
please submit your entries,
请提交您的参赛作品，
should be very, very exciting and we look forward to receiving your submissions.
非常令人兴奋，我们期待着收到你的参赛作品。
Okay, so in addition to that, those technical components of the course,
好的，除了这门课的那些技术部分，
we have three remaining guest lectures
我们还有三节客座讲座，
to round out our lecture series.
来结束我们的系列讲座。
We heard an amazing talk yesterday by Sadhana from themis AI
我们昨天听到了来自 Themis AI 的 Sadhana 令人惊叹的演讲，
on robust and trustworthy deep learning.
关于稳健和值得信赖的深度学习。
Today we're going to hear from Ramin Hasani, from Vanguard,
今天，我们将听取来自 Vanguard 公司的 Ramin Hasani 的演讲，
who's going to talk about the new age of statistics
他将谈论统计学的新时代，
and what that can mean for deep learning algorithms.
以及这对深度学习算法意味着什么。
Tomorrow, we'll have two awesome guest lectures
明天，我们将有两场精彩的嘉宾演讲，
from Dilip Krishnan from Google
来自 Google 的 Dilip Krishnan ，
and to round it out from Daniela Rus, the director of MIT CSAIL herself,
以及来自 MIT CSAIL 主管 Daniela Rus ，
yes, some, we know that there are many fans of Daniela in the audience, us included.
是的，一些，我们知道观众中有很多 Daniela 的粉丝，包括我们。
So please attend, these should be really awesome talk
所以请出席，这些应该是非常棒的演讲，
and you'll get to hear more about the cutting edge of research in deep learning.
你将听到更多关于深度学习研究的前沿。
Okay, so that rounds out all the logistical and program announcements that I wanted to make.
好了，这就是我想要宣布的所有后勤和项目公告。
Now we can really dive into the fun stuff,
现在我们可以真正深入到有趣的东西，
the technical content for this class.
这门课的技术内容。
So, so far, in introduction to deep learning,
到目前为止，在深度学习入门中，
you've learned about the foundations of neural network algorithms
你已经了解了神经网络算法的基础，
and also got a taste
也领略了，
for how deep learning has already started to make an impact across many different research areas and applications,
深度学习已经开始对许多不同的研究领域和应用产生影响，
from advances in autonomous vehicles,
从自动驾驶汽车的进步，
to think about, to think about applications in medicine and healthcare,
到思考医学和医疗保健应用，
to reinforcement learning,
到强化学习，
that is changing the way that we think about gains and play,
这在改变我们思考收益和游戏的方式，
to new generative modeling advances,
到新的生成性建模的进步，
to robotics,
到机器人技术，
to many, many other applications,
再到许多其他应用，
like natural language processing, finance, security and more.
比如自然语言处理、金融、安全等。
What we really hope you come away with from this course is
我们真正希望你从这门课程中学到的是，
a concrete understanding of how deep neural networks work
对深度神经网络如何工作的具体理解，
and how these foundational algorithms are really enabling these advances across this multitude of disciplines.
以及这些基础算法是如何真正实现这些跨众多学科的进步的。
And you've seen in this class and in this program,
你们在这门课和这个课程中已经看到，
that we've dealt with neural networks as a way,
我们把神经网络作为一种方式，
as an algorithmic way,
作为一种算法方式，
to think about going from input data in the form of signals or measurements,
来考虑从输入数据中提取信号或测量数据的形式，
that we can derive from sensors of our world,
这些数据可以从我们世界的传感器中获得，
to directly produce some sort of decision,
直接产生某种决策，
that could be a prediction, like a class label or a numerical value,
可以是预测，比如类别标签或数值，
or it could be an action itself, like in the case of reinforcement learning.
也可以是动作本身，就像强化学习的情况一样。
We've also seen the inverse,
我们也看到了相反的情况，
where we can think about now building neural network algorithms,
我们现在可以考虑建立神经网络算法，
that can go from a desired prediction or a desired action
它可以从所需的预测或所需的操作，
to try to generate new data instances,
来尝试生成新的数据实例，
as is the case with generative modeling.
就像生成性建模一样。
Now, taking a step back right in both these cases,
现在，在这两种情况下退后一步，
whether we're going from data to decision or the reverse,
无论我们是从数据到决策还是从数据到决策，
neural networks can be thought of as very powerful function approximators.
神经网络可以被认为是非常强大的函数逼近器。
What that means,
这意味着什么，
and to get at this in more detail,
为了更详细地了解这一点，
we have to go back to a really famous theorem in computer science and in the theory of neural networks,
我们必须回到计算机科学和神经网络理论中非常著名的一个定理，
that was this theorem that was presented in 1989
那就是 1989 年提出的这个定理，
and it generated quite the stir in the field,
它在该领域引起了相当大的轰动，
this theorem is called the universal approximation theorem.
这个定理叫做万能逼近定理。
And what it states is that,
它所说的是，
if we start with a neural network,
如果我们从神经网络开始，
with just a single hidden layer,
只有一个隐藏层，
that single layer neural network is sufficient to approximate any function.
这个单层神经网络足以逼近任何函数。
Now, in this class,
现在，在这门课上，
we've been thinking about not single layer neural networks,
我们考虑的不是单层神经网络，
but rather deep models that stack multiple of these hidden layers together,
而是将多个隐藏层堆叠在一起的深层模型，
but this theorem says, oh, you don't even need that,
但是这个定理说，你甚至不需要它，
all you need is a single layer,
你只需要一个层，
and if you believe that,
如果你相信这一点，
any problem can be simply reduced to this idea of mapping an input to an output through some function,
任何问题都可以简单地归结为通过某个函数将输入映射到输出的想法，
that neural network can exist,
这种神经网络可以存在，
the universal approximation theorem states that,
万能逼近定理指出，
there is some neural network,
存在某种神经网络，
with a sufficient number of neurons that can approximate any arbitrary function.
有足够数量的神经元可以逼近任何任意函数。
Now this is an incredibly powerful result,
这是一个令人难以置信的强大的结果，
but if we look more closely at this and dig a little further,
但如果我们更仔细地观察并深入挖掘一下，
you can start to see that,
你可以开始看到，
there are a few caveats that we have to keep in mind.
我们必须牢记一些警告。
First of all,
首先，我要说的是，
this theorem makes no guarantees on how many units,
这个定理不能保证你需要多少个单元，
how many neurons in that layer you need to solve such a problem.
在那一层有多少神经元才能解决这样的问题。
Furthermore, it says,
此外，它说，
okay, how do, it doesn't answer the question of how we can actually define that neural network,
它没有回答我们如何真正定义那个神经网络的问题，
how do we find the ways to support that architecture,
我们如何找到支持该体系结构的方法，
all it claims is tha such a neural network exists.
它所宣称的就是这样一个神经网络的存在。
But we know that,
但我们知道，
using gradient descent and some of the tools that we learned about in this class,
使用梯度下降和我们在这节课上学到的一些工具，
that finding those weights is not always a straightforward problem,
找到这些权重并不总是一个简单的问题，
it can be very complex, very nonlinear, very non convex
它可以是非常复杂的，非常非线性的，非常非凸的，
and thinking about how we actually achieve that,
并且思考我们如何真正实现这一点，
training of the neural network is a very, very hard problem.
神经网络的训练是一个非常非常困难的问题。
Secondly, what is really important about this theorem is that,
其次，这个定理的真正重要之处在于，
it does not make any guarantees on how well that network would generalize to new tasks,
它不能保证网络对新任务的泛化程度，
all it says is that,
它所说的是，
given this desired mapping from input to output,
给定从输入到输出的所需映射，
we can find some neural network that exists,
我们可以找到一些神经网络，
no guarantees on its performance in other tasks or in other settings.
它在其他任务或其他设置中的性能不存在保证。
And I think that this theorem,
我认为这个定理，
this idea of the universal approximation theorem and its underlying caveats,
这个万能逼近定理的想法及其潜在的警告，
is a perfect example
是一个完美的例子，
of what can be thought of as the possible effects of the overhype in artificial intelligence and in deep learning.
可以被认为是人工智能和深度学习中过度炒作可能产生的影响。
And now here you've become part of this community, right,
现在你已经成为这个社区的一部分，
that's interested in advancing the state of deep learning and AI,
对推动深度学习和人工智能的状态感兴趣，
and I think collectively
我认为，总的来说，
we need to be extremely careful in how we think about these algorithms,
我们需要非常谨慎地考虑这些算法，
how we market them, how we advertise them,
我们如何营销它们，我们如何宣传它们，
how we use them in the problems that we care about.
我们如何在我们关心的问题中使用它们。
And while universal approximation tells us,
虽然万能逼近定理告诉我们，
and that neural networks can be very, very powerful
神经网络可以非常、非常强大，
and generates a lot of excitement around this idea,
并围绕这个想法产生许多兴奋点，
at a time historically, actually provided false hope to the computer science and AI community,
在历史上，神经网络实际上给计算机科学和人工智能社区提供了错误的希望，
that neural networks could solve any problem of any complexity in the real world.
认为神经网络可以解决现实世界中任何复杂的问题。
Now, I think it goes without saying,
现在，我认为不用说，
that such overhype can be extremely dangerous.
这种过度炒作可能是极其危险的。
And in fact, it's not only the effect is not only in the course of research,
事实上，这不仅在研究过程中产生了影响，
but also potentially at society at large.
而且可能会在整个社会产生影响。
So this is why that today, for the rest of this lecture,
这就是为什么今天，在这节课剩下的时间里，
I really want to focus on some of the limitations of deep learning algorithms,
我真的想重点关注深度学习算法的一些局限性，
that you've learned about this over the course of this class.
你们在这节课上已经学到的。
And I want to not only stop there, I want to extend beyond that,
我不仅想止步于此，我还想超越这一点，
to see how these limitations motivate new opportunities,
看看这些限制如何激发新的机会，
for new research that can be aimed at addressing some of those problems and overcoming them.
对于新的研究，解决其中的一些问题并克服它们。
So, to start,
因此，首先，
one of my favorite examples of a potential danger of deep neural networks,
我最喜欢的深层神经网络潜在危险的例子之一，
comes from this paper,
来自这篇论文，
comes from this paper that says,
这篇论文说，
understanding deep neural networks requires rethinking generalization.
理解深层神经网络需要重新思考概括。
This paper proposes a really elegant and simple experiment,
本文提出了一个非常优雅和简单的实验，
that highlights this notion of generalization and its limitations with deep learning models.
突出了这种泛化概念及其在深度学习模型中的局限性。
So what they do in this paper is that,
因此，他们在这篇论文中所做的是，
they took images from this large dataset called imagenet,
他们从一个名为 imagenet 的大型数据集中获取图像，
and each of these images is associated with a particular label,
这些图像中的每一张都与一个特定的标签相关联，
dog, banana, dog, tree,
狗，香蕉，狗，树，
as you can see here.
就像你在这里看到的。
Then what, what the authors of this paper did was that,
然后，这篇论文的作者所做的是，
they considered each of these image examples,
他们考虑了这些每一个图像的例子，
and for every image in the data,
对于数据中的每一幅图像，
they took a k sided die,
他们取了 k 边骰子，
where k is the number of possible class labels in this data set,
其中 k 是该数据集中可能的类别标签的数量，
and use that die to randomly assign new labels to each of these instances,
并使用骰子将新标签随机分配给这些实例中的每一个，
now, all of the labels have been completely scrambled, right,
现在，所有的标签都被完全打乱了，
they're doing this random sampling,
他们进行随机抽样，
assigning these brand new labels to these images,
为这些图像分配这些全新的标签，
and what this means is that,
这意味着，
the labels that are associated with an image,
与图像相关联的标签，
as you see, are completely random with respect to what is actually in that image,
如你所见，相对于图像中的实际内容是完全随机的，
then what they did,
然后他们所做的，
and if you know here,
如果你知道这里，
is you can have instances,
你可以拥有实例，
because you have overlaps of multiple instances corresponding to the same class,
因为你有多个实例的重叠对应于同一个类，
but now when you introduce randomness,
但是现在，当你引入随机性时，
you can have two instances of the same class,
你可以拥有同一类的两个实例，
that now end up with completely different labels,
它们现在有完全不同的标签，
dog here maps to banana in one case and to tree in another case,
狗在这里，在一个情况下映射到香蕉，在另一个情况下映射到树，
so literally,
因此，从字面上讲，
they completely, completely randomizing the labels entirely,
他们完全、完全地将标签随机化，
with that in hand,
有了这一点，
what they did was they tried to fit a deep neural network model
他们所做的就是尝试将深度神经网络模型，
to the sampled data from this dataset, imagenet,
与来自数据集 imagenet 的采样数据相匹配，
and they vary the degree of randomness,
它们的随机性程度，
ranging from the preserved original labels to completely random,
从保留下来的原始标签到完全随机，
and then they took the resulting model,
然后他们得到了最终的模型，
looked at its performance on the test set,
看看它在测试集上的表现，
an independent data set,
这是一个独立的数据集，
where now we're given new images
现在我们得到了新的图像，
and the task of the network is to predict the associated label,
网络的任务是预测相关的标签，
and as you can expect,
正如你所预料的那样，
the accuracy of the model on this independent test set decreases
独立测试集上的模型的准确性会降低，
as you introduce more and more randomness into the label process,
当你在标签过程中引入越来越多的随机性时，
what was really interesting, however,
然而，真正有趣的是，
was what they saw when they now looked not at the test set,
当他们现在不看测试集时看到的是什么，
but at the training set,
而是在训练集上，
and this is what they found,
这就是他们的发现，
that no matter how much they randomized these labels,
无论他们对这些标签进行了多大程度的随机化，
the neural network model, when trained on that resulting data,
神经网络模型在得到的数据上进行训练时，
was able to get 100% accuracy on the training set,
都能够在训练集上获得 100% 的准确率，
what this means is that,
这意味着，
these neural network models can really do this perfect fitting,
这些神经网络模型真的可以进行这种完美的拟合，
this very powerful function approximation.
这种非常强大的函数逼近。
And I think that this is a very powerful example,
我认为这是一个非常有力的例子，
because it shows once again,
因为它再次表明，
like the universal approximation theorem,
就像万能逼近定理一样，
that deep neural nets can perfectly fit to any function,
深度神经网络可以完美地适用于任何函数，
even if that function is defined by entirely random labels.
即使该函数是由完全随机的标签定义的。
Now you'll note that,
现在你将注意到，
this difference between the training set performance and the test set performance
训练集性能和测试集性能之间的差异，
captures this idea of generalization,
捕捉到这种泛化思想，
what is the limit of the neural network with respect to function fitting
神经网络在函数拟合方面的极限是什么，
and how it actually performs on unseen data.
以及它在未知数据上的实际表现是什么。
And to drive this point home even further,
为了进一步阐明这一点，
again, we can really understand neural networks simply as functional approximators,
我们可以简单地将神经网络理解为函数逼近器，
and what the universal approximation theorem is telling us is that,
而万能逼近定理告诉我们的是，
neural networks are just really, really, really good at doing this job.
神经网络非常非常擅长做这项工作。
So if we consider this example here,
所以，如果我们考虑这个例子，
where I've shown these data points in this 2D space,
我已经在这个二维空间中展示了这些数据点，
we can always train a neural network
我们总是可以训练神经网络，
to learn what is the most likely position of the data within this space,
来学习数据在这个空间中最可能的位置，
within this realm that it has seen examples before,
在它以前见过的这个领域中，
such that, if we get,
这样，如果我们得到，
if we give the model a new data point here in purple,
如果我们给模型一个新的紫色数据点，
we can expect that,
我们可以预期，
the neural network is going to generate a reasonable prediction of the estimate for that data point,
神经网络将生成对该数据点的估计的合理预测，
now, the challenge becomes,
现在，挑战变成了，
what if you now start to extend beyond this landscape,
如果你现在开始超越这一领域，
beyond the region that you have information, that you have data examples,
超越你拥有信息的区域，你拥有数据例子，
well, we have no guarantees on what the training data looks like in these regions,
我们不能保证这些地区的训练数据是什么样子的，
and this is in fact one of the large limitations that exist in modern deep neural networks,
这实际上是现代深度神经网络存在的巨大限制之一，
that they're very, very effective at functional approximation in regions when we have training data,
当我们有训练数据时，它们在区域的函数逼近方面非常有效，
but we can't make guarantees on their performance out of those regions.
但我们不能保证他们在这些地区的表现。
And so this raises this question,
这就提出了这个问题，
which again, ties back to so in lecture yesterday,
在昨天的课上，
of how can we derive methods, that tell us,
我们如何才能得出方法，可以告诉我们，
when the network doesn't know, when it needs more information, needs more examples.
网络何时不知道，当它需要更多信息，需要更多例子。
Building off this idea a little further,
在这个想法的基础上，
I think there's often this common conception,
我认为经常有这样一个通用的概念，
which can indeed be inflated by the media,
确实可以被媒体夸大，
that deep learning is basically this magic solution,
深度学习就是这个神奇的解决方案，
alchemy,
炼金术，
it can be the be all end, all solution to any problem,
它可以是任何问题的最终解决方案，
but this spawns the belief that,
但这让人相信，
if we take some data examples
如果我们拿一些数据例子，
and apply some training architecture to it,
并对其应用一些训练架构，
train the resulting model,
训练产生的模型，
turn the crank on the deep learning algorithm,
转向深度学习算法，
that will spit out some beautiful, excellent results,
它将产生一些漂亮的、优秀的结果，
solving our problem,
解决我们的问题，
but this is simply not how deep learning works,
但这根本不是深度学习的运作方式，
there's this common idea of garbage in garbage out,
有一种通常的垃圾输入导致垃圾输出的想法，
if your data is noisy,
如果你的数据很杂乱，
if you have insufficient data,
如果你没有足够的数据，
if you try to build this very large neural network model to operate on the data,
如果你试图建立一个非常大的神经网络模型来操作数据，
you're not going to guarantee performance results at the outset.
你就不能从保证性能结果。
And this motivates one of the most pertinent failure modes of modern deep neural nets,
这激发了现代深层神经网络最恰当的失败模型之一，
and it highlights just how much they depend on the underlying data that they're trained with.
它突显了它们对训练所用的基础数据的依赖程度。
So let's say we have this image of a dog
让我们假设我们有一只狗的图像，
and we are going to pass it into a CNN architecture,
我们将把它传递到 CNN 的架构中，
and our task is now to try to colorize this image,
我们的任务是尝试对这张图像着色，
black and white image of a dog and produce a colored output,
使用狗的黑白图像产生彩色输出，
this can be the result,
这可能就是结果，
look closely at this resulting image,
仔细观察这张生成的图像，
anyone notice anything unusual about the dog?
有人注意到这只狗有什么不寻常的地方吗？
Yes.
是。
The ear is green,
耳朵是绿色的，
awesome observation, anything else?
很棒的观察，还有别的吗？
Yes.
是。
Yeah, the chin is pink or purple.
是的，下巴是粉红色或紫色的。
And so two different instances pointed out by two different people
所以两个不同的人指出了两个不同的例子，
of things that don't really align,
这些东西并不是真正一致的，
why could this be the case.
为什么会是这样呢。
In particular, if we look at the data that this model was trained with,
尤其是，如果我们看一下这个模型训练时使用的数据，
amongst the images of the dogs,
在狗的图像中，
many of those images are going to be probably
许多图像可能是，
of the dogs sticking their tongues out or having some grass in the background,
狗伸出舌头或背景中有一些草，
and as a result, the CNN model may have mapped that region around the chin to be pink in color
因此， CNN 的模型可能已经将下巴周围的区域映射为粉色，
or around the ears to be green in color,
或将耳朵周围的区域映射为绿色，
and what this example really highlights in thinking about this contrast
这个例子突出显示了这种差异，
between what the training data looks like and what the predictive outputs can be.
训练数据看起来像什么和预测输出可能是什么。
Is that deep learning models,
这就是深度学习模式，
all they're doing is that,
它们所做的只是，
they're building up this representation,
它们建立这种表征，
based on the data that they have seen over the course of training.
基于它们在训练过程中看到的数据。
And that raises this question
这就提出了一个问题，
of how do neural networks effectively handle those instances,
神经网络如何有效地处理这些实例，
where they may not have seen enough information,
它们可能没有看到足够信息的情况，
they may be highly uncertain,
它们可能非常不确定，
and exactly as Sadhana motivated in yesterday's lecture and laid out beautifully,
正如 Sadhana 在昨天的课程中提到的，列出的，
this is highly relevant to real world safety critical scenarios,
这与现实世界的安全关键场景高度相关，
for example, in the case of autonomous driving,
例如，在自动驾驶的情况下，
where cars that are on autopilot can or in autonomous mode
处于自动驾驶模式的汽车可能会或处于自动驾驶模式，
can end up crashing,
最终可能会发生碰撞，
with the results often being fatal or having very significant significant consequences.
结果往往是致命的或具有非常重大的后果。
In this particular instance to really highlight this further from a few years ago,
在这个特殊的情况下，真正从几年前进一步突出这一点，
there was the case of an autonomous vehicle that resulted in a fatal accident,
有一起自动驾驶汽车的案例，导致了一起致命的事故，
where it, it crashed into a pylon,
它撞上了一个塔架，
a construction pylon that was present on the road,
一个出现在路上的建筑塔架，
and it turned out that,
事实证明，
when they looked back at the data that was used to train the resulting neural network,
当他们回顾用于训练神经网络的数据时，
that was used to control the car,
这个神经网络用于控制汽车，
that in those training examples,
在这些训练例子中，
the Google street view images of that particular region of the road
Google 街景图像中该特定区域的道路，
did not have those construction barriers and construction pylons,
没有那些建筑障碍物和建筑塔架，
that resulted in the car crashing in the end.
最终导致汽车相撞。
And so, again, this idea of how disparities and issues with the training data
因此，这种关于训练数据的差异和问题
can lead to these downstream consequences
如何导致这些下游后果的想法，
is a really prominent failure mode with neural network systems,
对于神经网络系统来说是一个非常突出的失败模型，
and it's exactly these types of failure modes that motivated
正是这些类型的失败模型促使人们
the need for understanding uncertainty in neural network systems.
需要了解神经网络系统中的不确定性。
And this was what you learned about in yesterday's lecture
这就是你们在昨天的课程中学到的，
and hopefully have gotten in depth experience with through the software lab,
希望你们已经通过软件实验获得了深入的经验，
highlighting the importance of developing robust methods
强调开发强大的方法，
to understand these metrics of uncertainty and risk,
来了解这些不确定性和风险度量的重要性，
and how they can be really important for safety critical applications
以及它们对于安全关键应用程序是多么重要，
from autonomy to medicine to facial recognition,
从自主到医学再到面部识别等，
as you're exploring,
就像你正在探索的那样，
and how these downstream consequences
以及这些下游后果如何从根本上
are linked fundamentally to issues of data imbalance, feature imbalance and noise.
与数据不平衡、功能不平衡和噪音问题联系在一起。
So, overall,
所以，总体而言，
I think that what these instances and these considerations point us to is
我认为这些情况和这些考虑向我们指出的是，
the susceptibilities of neural networks to succumb to these failure modes.
神经网络的敏感性，屈服于这些失败模式。
The final failure mode that I'd like to consider and highlight is
我想要考虑和强调的最后一个失败模式是，
this idea of adversarial examples.
这种对抗性例子的想法。
The intuition and the key idea here is that,
这里的直觉和关键思想是，
we can take a data instance, for example an image,
我们可以拿一个数据实例，例如一个图像，
which if deployed and inputted into a standard CNN,
如果部署并输入到标准的 CNN 中，
is going to be predicted to contain a temple with 97% probability,
将以 97% 的概率预测包含一座寺庙，
what we can do is,
我们所能做的是，
now apply some tiny perturbation in the form of random noise, choice random noise to that original image,
以随机噪声，选择随机噪声的形式对原始图像施加一些微小的扰动，
that then results in a perturbed image,
然后产生一个扰动的图像，
which to us humans appears visually largely the same,
对我们人类来说，这在视觉上看起来大体相同，
but if you pass that resulting image back to that same neural network,
但如果你把得到的图像返回给同一个神经网络，
it produces a prediction that completely does not align with what is actually in the image,
它产生的预测与图像中的实际情况完全不一致，
predicting ostrich, label of ostrich with 98% probability.
预测鸵鸟标签的概率为 98% 。
And this is this notion of an adversarial attack or an adversarial perturbation,
这就是对抗性攻击或对抗性扰动的概念，
what exactly is this perturbation doing,
这种微扰究竟在做什么，
remember that when we train neural networks using gradient descent,
当我们使用梯度下降来训练神经网络时，
the task is to optimize or minimize some loss function and objective,
任务是优化或最小化某些损失函数和目标，
and the goal in standard gradient descent is to say,
标准梯度下降的目标是，
okay, how can I change the weights of the neural network to decrease the loss to optimize that objective,
好的，我如何改变神经网络的权重来减少损失，从而优化这个目标，
we are specifically concerned with changing those weights W in a way to minimize our loss,
我们特别关注以某种方式改变这些权重 W ，以将我们的损失降至最低，
if you look closer here,
如果你仔细看这里，
we are considering only the changes of the weights with respect to the input data and the corresponding label x and y,
我们只考虑相对于输入数据的权重以及对应的标签 x 和 y ，
in contrast, in thinking about adversarial attacks,
相比之下，在思考对抗性攻击时，
we now ask a different question,
我们现在提出了一个不同的问题，
how can we modify that input data, for example that image,
我们如何修改输入数据，例如图像，
in order to increase the error in the network prediction,
以在网络预测中增加误差，
concretely, how does a small change of tiny perturbation in the input data x
具体地说，输入数据 x 中微小的微扰是如何，
result in a maximal increase in the loss,
导致损失最大幅度的增加，
what that means is that,
这意味着，
we can fix the weights,
我们可以固定权重，
keep the network the same,
保持网络不变，
and look at how we can perturb and change and manipulate that input data
并研究如何干扰、更改和操纵输入数据，
to try to increase that loss function.
以尝试增加损失函数。
An extension of this idea was developed and presented by a group of students right here at MIT,
这个想法的扩展是由 MIT 的一群学生开发和提出的，
where they took this idea of adversarial perturbation
他们利用对抗性微扰的想法，
and created an algorithm,
创造了一个算法，
that could synthesize not only adversarial realizations in 2D,
不仅可以在二维内合成对抗性实现，
but actually in 3D,
而且可以在三维内，
using a set of different transformations,
使用一组不同的变换，
like rotations, color changes, other types of perturbations,
比如旋转，颜色变化，其他类型的微扰，
then, using those learned perturbations,
然后，利用这些学习的扰动，
they took those information
他们获取了这些信息，
and actually physically synthesized objects using 3D printing,
并使用三维打印合成了对象，
that were designed to be adversarial examples for a neural network,
这些被设计为神经网络的对抗性例子，
and so they printed 3D, printed a bunch of these examples of turtles,
所以他们打印了三维，打印了一堆这些乌龟的例子，
3D physical objects,
三维物理物体，
such that images of those would be completely fooling neural network,
这样那些图像就会完全愚弄神经网络，
that looked at that image and tried to classify the correct label,
看着图像，试图分类正确的标签，
and so this shows that this notion of adversarial examples and perturbation
这表明，这种对抗性例子和扰动的概念
can extend to different domains in the real world,
可以扩展到现实世界中的不同领域，
where now we can think about constructing these synthetic examples,
现在我们可以考虑构建这些合成例子，
that are designed to probe at the weaknesses of neural networks and expose their vulnerabilities.
旨在探索神经网络的弱点并揭示其脆弱性。
Finally, and we've discussed a lot about this idea yesterday as well,
最后，我们昨天也讨论了很多关于这个想法的问题，
is this notion of algorithmic bias,
这种算法偏差的概念，
the fact that as AI systems become more broadly deployed in society,
随着人工智能系统在社会上得到更广泛的部署，
that they're susceptible to significant biases
它们很容易受到重大偏差的影响，
resulting from many of those issues that I highlighted earlier,
是我之前强调的许多问题造成的，
and these can lead to very real detrimental consequences,
而这些可能会导致非常真实的有害后果，
as we've been exploring throughout this course in both labs and lectures.
正如我们在这门课程的实验和课程中一直在探索的那样。
So the examples that I covered so far
因此，我到目前为止所举的例子
are certainly not an exhaustive list of all the limitations of neural networks,
肯定不是神经网络所有局限性的详尽清单，
but I'd like to think of these not strictly as limitations,
但我不想把这些严格地看作是限制，
but rather an invitation and a motivation for new innovation,
而是对新创新的邀请和动力，
creative solutions that are aimed at trying to tackle some of these questions,
这些创新和创造性解决方案旨在试图解决其中一些问题，
which are indeed open problems in AI and deep learning research today,
这些问题确实是当今人工智能和深度学习研究中的悬而未决的问题，
specifically, we've tackled and already thought about ways to address issues of bias and uncertainty in neural networks.
特别是，我们已经解决并已经考虑了解决神经网络中的偏见和不确定性问题的方法。
And now for the remainder of this talk,
在接下来的演讲中，
I want to focus on some of the really exciting new frontiers of deep learning,
我想把重点放在深度学习的一些非常令人兴奋的新领域上，
tackling some of these additional limitations that are introduced.
解决引入的一些额外限制。
The first being this idea,
第一个想法，
that stems from this idea of the size and scale of neural networks.
源于对神经网络的规模和规模的看法。
They rely heavily on data,
它们严重依赖数据，
they're massive
它们是海量的，
and as a result it can be difficult to understand,
因此可能很难理解，
what is the underlying structure, if any, that the neural network is picking up on.
神经网络挑选的底层结构是什么。
And so there's a very, very exciting line of work now,
现在有一项非常非常令人兴奋的工作，
that is focused on introducing structure and more information from prior human knowledge into neural network architectures
将结构和更多来自先前人类知识的信息引入神经网络结构，
to enable them to become much smaller, more compact, more expressive, more efficient.
使它们变得更小、更紧凑、更有表现力、更高效。
And we're going to see a bit of this in today's lecture,
我们将在今天的演讲中看到这一点，
but also in our following guest lecture by Ramin,
也会在我们接下来的 Ramin 的客座演讲中看到这一点，
where he will talk about this idea of structural encoding
他将在那里谈到结构编码的想法，
and how that can result in highly expressive and efficient neural network architectures.
以及它如何产生高度表达和高效的神经网络结构。
The second issue that I'm going to talk about and discuss
我要谈的第二个问题，
and is very related to this problem of scale and structure
与规模和结构的问题密切相关，
is how we can encourage neural networks to now extrapolate more effectively beyond data,
我们现在如何鼓励神经网络在数据之外更有效地进行推断，
and this will tie very neatly into some of the ideas we've been discussing around generative AI,
这将非常巧妙地与我们一直在讨论的关于生成性人工智能的一些想法联系在一起，
and will be the last topic that I'm going to discuss in the remainder of today's lecture.
这将是我将在今天剩余的演讲中讨论的最后一个话题。
Okay, so let's focus on this first, first concept,
好的，让我们先来关注一下这个概念，
of how we can leverage more of our human domain knowledge
我们如何利用更多的人类领域知识
to encode greater structure into deep learning algorithms.
来将更大的结构编码到深度学习算法中。
Turns out we've already seen examples of this in the course so far,
到目前为止，我们已经在课程中看到了这方面的例子，
particularly highlighted in CNN,
特别是 CNN 中，
used for spatial processing and visual data.
强调的用于空间处理和视觉数据的例子。
As we saw, CNNs were introduced
正如我们所看到的， CNN 被引入，
to be a highly efficient architecture for capturing spatial dependencies in data,
作为一种高效的架构来捕获数据中的空间依赖关系，
and the core idea behind CNN was this notion of convolution,
CNN 背后的核心思想是卷积的概念，
how it would relate spatially similar and adjacent portions of an input image to each other
它如何将输入图像的空间相似和相邻部分相互关联，
through this efficient convolution operation.
通过这种有效的卷积运算。
And we saw that convolution was able to be effective at extracting local features from visual data,
我们看到卷积能够有效地从视觉数据中提取局部特征，
and then using this local feature extraction to then enable downstream predictive tasks,
然后使用该局部特征提取来实现下游预测任务，
like classification, object detection and so forth.
比如分类、目标检测等。
What about now, instead of images,
现在，如果不是图像，
if we consider more irregular data structures,
我们考虑更不规则的数据结构，情况会怎样，
that can be encoded in different ways beyond 2D grids of pixels,
它可以通过二维像素网格以外的不同方式进行编码，
graphs are a particularly powerful way of encoding structural information,
图是一种编码结构信息的特别强大的方法，
and it can be in many cases,
在许多情况下，
that the notion of a graph or a network is very important to the problem that we may be considering,
图或网络的概念对于我们可能正在考虑的问题非常重要，
graphs as a structure and as an example for representing data
图作为一种结构和表示数据的示例，
are really all around us,
确实存在于我们周围，
across many different applications,
跨越许多不同的应用程序，
ranging from social networks,
范围从社交网络，
defining how we are all connected to each other,
定义了我们彼此之间的联系方式，
to state machines,
到状态机，
that describe how a process can transition from one state to another,
描述一个过程如何从一个状态转换到另一个状态，
to metrics and models of human mobility, urban transport,
到人类流动性、城市交通的度量和模型，
to chemical molecules and biological networks.
到化学分子和生物网络。
And the motivation across all these examples is that,
所有这些例子的动机是，
so many instances of real world data fall into naturally this idea of a network or graph structure,
如此多的真实世界数据的实例自然地落入这种网络或图形结构的概念中，
but that this structure cannot be readily incorporated or captured by standard data encodings or geometries,
但这种结构不容易被标准的数据编码或几何图形结合或捕获，
and so we're going to talk a little bit about graphs as a structure
因此，我们将稍微讨论一下将图作为一种结构，
and how we can try to represent this information encoded in a graph
以及如何尝试将编码在图形中的信息表示出来，
to build neural networks that are capable of handling these data types.
以构建能够处理这些数据类型的神经网络。
To see how we can do this and, and approach this problem,
为了看看我们如何做到这一点，并处理这个问题，
let's go back for a moment to the CNN,
让我们花一点时间回到 CNN ，
in CNN, we saw that we have this rectangular 2D kernel,
在 CNN 中，我们看到了这个矩形的二维内核，
and what it effectively does is,
它所做的是，
it slides across the image,
它有效地在图像中滑动，
paying attention and picking up to features that exist across this 2D grid,
关注并拾取存在于这个二维网格中的特征，
and all this function is doing is that,
这个函数所做的是，
element wise multiplication that defines the convolution operation,
定义卷积运算的元素乘法，
and intuitively, we can think about convolution as this visualization of sliding this kernel,
直观地说，我们可以把卷积看作滑动这个核心的可视化，
iteratively patch by patch across the image,
在图像上一块一块迭代，
continuing on to try to pick up on informative features that are captured in this 2D pixel space.
继续尝试提取在这二维像素空间中捕捉到的信息特征。
This core idea of convolution in sliding this this feature extraction filter is
卷积在滑动中这个特征提取过滤器的核心思想是，
at the heart of now how we can extend this idea to graph based data,
我们如何将这个思想扩展到基于图形的核心，
this motivates a very recent type of neural network architecture called graph convolutional networks,
这激发了一种称为图卷积网络的最新类型的神经网络结构，
where the idea is very similar to standard CNNs,
其思想与标准的 CNN 非常相似，
we have some type of weight [kernel],
我们有某种权重的[核]，
and all it is is a matrix defined by neural network weights as before,
它只是一个像以前一样由神经网络权重定义的矩阵，
and now, rather than sliding that kernel across a 2D grid of pixels,
现在不是在二维像素网格上滑动内核，
the kernel goes around to different parts of the graph,
内核去到图形的不同部分，
defined by particular nodes,
由特定节点定义，
and it looks at what the neighbors of the of that node is,
它查看该节点的邻居是什么，
how it's connected to adjacent nodes,
它是如何连接到相邻节点的，
and the kernel is used to extract features from that local neighborhood within the graph
而核被用来从图中的局部邻域中提取特征，
to then capture the relevant information within the structure.
然后捕获结构中的相关信息。
So we can visualize this concretely here,
所以我们可以在这里具体地看到这一点，
where now instead of seeing the 2D kernel looking at a particular patch of an image,
现在不是看到二维内核查看图像的特定块，
what I'm highlighting is how the kernel is paying attention to node and its local neighbors
我要强调的是内核是如何关注节点及其本地邻居的，
and effectively the graph convolution operation,
以及有效的图形卷积操作，
what it's doing is picking up on the local connectivity of a particular node
它所做的是拾取特定节点的局部连通性，
and learning weights that are associated with those edges, defining that local connectivity,
并学习与这些边相关联的权重，定义该局部连通性，
the kernel is just then applied iteratively to each node in the graph,
然后，将内核迭代应用于图中的每个节点，
trying to extract information about the local connectivity,
试图提取有关本地连接性的信息，
such that we can go around and around
这样我们就可以四处走动，
and at the end start to bring all this information together in aggregation
最后开始把所有这些信息聚集在一起，
to then encode and update the weights according to what the local observations were.
然后根据当地的观测结果对权重进行编码和更新。
The key idea is very, very similar to the standard convolution operation,
它的关键思想非常非常类似于标准的卷积运算，
where this way kernel,
这种方法是核心，
all it's doing is a feature extraction procedure,
它所做的是一个特征提取过程，
that's now defined by nodes and edges in this graph,
现在由这个图中的节点和边来定义，
rather than a 2D grid of pixels in an image.
而不是图像中的二维像素网格。
This idea of graph encoding and graph convolution is very exciting and very powerful
图形编码和图形卷积的想法非常令人兴奋和强大的，
in terms of now how we can extend this to real world settings,
就我们现在如何将其扩展到现实世界的设置而言，
that are defined by data sets,
它有数据集定义，
that naturally lend themselves to this graph like structure.
这些数据集自然地适合于这个图结构。
So to highlight some of those applications across a variety of domains,
为了强调其中一些在不同领域的应用，
the first example I'd like to draw attention to is in the chemical and biological sciences,
我想要引起注意的第一个例子是在化学和生物科学中，
where now if we think about the structure of a molecule, right,
如果我们考虑一个分子结构，
it's defined by atoms,
它是由原子定义的，
and those atoms are individually connected to each other according to molecular bonds,
这些原子根据分子键相互连接，
and it turns out that we can design graph neural networks,
事实证明，我们可以设计图形神经网络，
that can effectively build representations of molecules,
它可以有效地构建分子的表示，
in the same operation of this graph convolution
以这个图卷积的相同操作，
to build up an informative representation of chemical structures,
建立化学结构的信息表示，
this very same idea of graph convolution was recently applied to the problem of drug discovery,
图形卷积的这个想法最近也被应用到了药物发现的问题上，
and in fact, out of work here at MIT,
事实上，在 MIT 的工作中也是如此，
it turned out that we can define graph neural network architectures,
事实证明，我们可以定义图形神经网络结构，
that can look at data of small molecule drugs
它可以查看小分子药物的数据，
and then look at new data sets
然后查看新的数据集，
to try to predict and discover new therapeutic compounds that have potent activity,
试图预测和发现具有强大活性的新治疗化合物，
such as killing bacteria and functioning as antibiotics.
比如杀菌和用作抗生素。
Beyond this example,
除了这个例子，
another recent application of graph neural networks has been in traffic prediction,
图神经网络最近的另一个应用是在交通预测中，
where the goal is to look at streets and intersections as nodes and edges defined by graph
其中的目标是将街道和十字路口视为图定义的节点和边，
and apply graph neural network to that structure and to patterns of mobility
并将图神经网络应用于该结构和移动模式，
to learn to predict what resulting traffic patterns could be.
以学习预测所产生的交通模式。
And indeed, in work from Google and DeepMind,
事实上，在谷歌和 DeepMind 的工作中，
this same modeling approach was able to result in significant improvements
同样的建模方法能够显著改善
in the prediction of ETA, estimated time of arrival in Google maps,
谷歌地图中 ETA 估计到达时间的预测，
so when you're looking at Google maps on your phone
因此，当你在手机上查看谷歌地图，
and predicting when you're going to arrive at some location,
并预测你何时将到达某个位置时，
what it's doing on the backend is applying this graph neural network architecture to look at data of traffic
它在后端所做的是应用这种图形神经网络体系结构来查看交通数据，
and make more informative predictions about how those patterns are changing over time.
并就这些模式如何随着时间的变化做出更有信息的预测。
A final and another recent example was in forecasting the spread of COVID-19,
最后一个也是最近的另一个例子是在预测 COVID-19 的传播中，
where, again, building off of this same idea of mobility patterns and contacts,
同样，基于同样的活动模式和连接，
graph neural networks were employed to look at not only spatial distributions of COVID spread,
图神经网络被用来不仅研究 COVID 传播的空间分布，
but also incorporate a temporal dimension,
还结合了一个时间维度，
so that researchers could effectively forecast what were the most likely areas to be affected by COVID-19,
以便研究人员可以有效地预测哪些地区最有可能受到 COVID-19 的影响，
and what time scales those effects were likely to occur on.
以及这些影响可能发生在什么时间尺度上。
So hopefully, this this highlights,
所以，希望这个强调，
this idea of how simple ideas about data structure can then be translated into new neural network architectures,
这样一个想法，关于数据结构可以转化为新的神经网络体系结构的简单想法，
that are specifically designed for particular problems in relevant application areas.
这些体系结构是专门为相关应用领域的特定问题设计的。
And this also lends very naturally to
这也自然而然地决定了，
how we can extend not beyond data to graphs,
我们如何才能扩展从数据到图形，
to now three dimensional data,
再到现在的三维数据，
which is often referred to as 3D point clouds,
这通常被称为三维点云，
and these are unordered sets of data,
这些都是无序的数据集，
and you can think about them as being scattered in 3D space,
你可以把它们想象成散布在三维空间中，
and it turns out that you can extend graph neural networks very naturally
事实证明，你可以非常自然地扩展图形神经网络，
to operate on 3D datasets, life point clouds,
以处理三维数据集，生命点云，
where the core idea is that,
其中的核心思想是，
you can dynamically compute meshes present in this 3D space
你可以动态计算这个三维空间中存在的网格，
using the same idea of graph convolution and graph neural networks.
使用图形卷积和图形神经网络的相同思想。
Okay, so hopefully with that run through of graph structure, graph neural networks,
好的，希望通过对图形结构、图形神经网络的了解，
you've started to get a little bit of idea about
你已经开始了解，
how inspection of the underlying structure of data and incorporation of our prior knowledge
如何使用数据基础结构的检查和我们的先验知识
can be used to inform new neural network architectures that are very well suited for particular tasks.
来为非常适合特定任务的新的神经网络体系结构提供信息。
On that, I want to spend the remaining of time of this lecture on our second new frontier,
关于这个，我想把这节课剩下的时间花在我们的第二个新领域，
focusing on generative AI.
重点是生成式 AI 。
So as we first introduced in the first lecture of this course and throughout,
正如我们在这门课程的第一节课中所介绍的那样，
I think that today we're really at this inflection point in AI,
我认为今天我们处于人工智能的转折点，
where we're seeing tremendous new capabilities,
我们看到了巨大的新功能，
with generative models in particular,
特别是生成式模型，
enabling new advances in a variety of fields,
使各种领域的新进展成为可能，
and I think we're just at the, at the casa of this inflection point,
我认为我们正处在这个转折点上，
in that in the coming years,
在未来的几年里，
we're going to see generative AI radically transform the landscape of our world, the landscape of our society.
我们将看到生成式 AI 从根本上改变我们世界的面貌，我们社会的面貌。
So today, in the remaining portion of the new frontiers lecture,
所以，今天，在新前沿课程的剩余部分，
we're going to focus specifically on a new class of generative models, diffusion models,
我们将专门关注一类新的生成式模型，扩散模型，
that are powering some of these latest advances in generative AI.
正在推动生成式 AI 的一些最新进展。
All right, to start,
好的，首先，
let's think back to the lecture on generative modeling,
让我们回顾一下关于生成式模型的课程，
where we focus primarily on two classes of generative models, VAEs and GANs,
我们主要关注两类生成式模型， VAE 和 GAN ，
what we didn't have time to go into into depth was
我们没有时间深入探讨的是，
what are some of the underlying limitations of these models VAEs and GANs.
这些 VAE 和 GAN 的潜在局限性是什么。
Turns out that there are three primary limitations,
事实证明，这里有三个主要限制，
the first is what we call mode collapse,
第一个是我们所说的模式崩溃，
meaning that in the generative process,
这意味着在生成过程中，
VAEs and GANs can kind of collapse down to this mode, this phase,
VAE 和 GAN 可以向下崩溃到这个模式，这个阶段，
where they're generating a lot of predictions,
它们会产生很多预测，
a lot of new samples that are very, very similar to each other,
很多彼此非常相似的新样本，
we often kind of think about this as regression to the average value or the most common value.
我们经常认为这是对平均值或最常见值的回归。
The second key limitation,
第二个关键限制，
as I kind of alluded to in our generative modeling lecture,
就像我在我们的生成式建模课程中提到的那样，
was that these models really struggle to generate radically new instances,
是这些模型真的很难生成全新的实例，
that are not similar to the training data, that are more diverse.
与训练数据不同，而更加多样化。
Finally, it turns out that GANs in particular and VAEs as well in practice can be very difficult to train,
最后，事实证明， GAN 以及 VAE 在实践中可能很难训练，
they're unstable, inefficient,
它们不稳定，效率低下，
and this leads to a lot of problems in practice,
这导致在实践中出现很多问题，
when thinking about how to scale these models.
当考虑如何扩展这些模型时。
These limitations then motivate a concrete set of challenges or criteria,
这些限制激发了一组具体的挑战或标准，
that we really want to meet when thinking about generative models,
当我们考虑生成式模型时，
we want our generative model to be stable, efficient to train,
我们希望我们的生成模型稳定、高效地进行训练，
we wanted to generate high quality samples,
我们希望生成高质量的样本，
that are synthetic and novel diverse,
这些样本是人工合成的，而且是新颖的多样化，
different from what the model has seen before in its training examples.
不同于该模型以前在其训练示例中看到的。
Today and tomorrow,
今天和明天，
we're going to focus on two very, very exciting new classes of generative models,
我们将关注两个非常令人兴奋的新的生成式模型，
that tackle these challenges head on.
它们将正面应对这些挑战。
Today, I'm going to specifically focus on diffusion models,
今天，我将特别关注扩散模型，
provide the intuition behind how they work,
提供它们工作原理背后的直觉，
where you may have seen them before
你以前可能在哪里见过它们，
and what are some of the advances that they're enabling.
以及它们带来了哪些进步。
And tomorrow, in the guest lecture from Google,
明天，在谷歌的客座演讲中，
we're going to hear from Dilip on another generative modeling approach,
我们将听到 Dilip 关于另一种生成式建模方法的演讲，
that's focused specifically on this task of text to image generation.
专门专注于从文本到图像生成的任务。
Okay, so let's get into it.
好的，所以让我们开始吧。
For diffusion models,
对于扩散模型，
I think it first helps us to compare back again to the models we've seen,
我认为它首先帮助我们再次与我们看到的模型进行比较，
the architectures we've seen and know about,
我们看到和了解的体系结构，
with VAEs and GANs that we talked about in lecture 4,
对于我们在第四讲中讨论的 VAE 和 GAN ，
the task is to generate examples, synthetic examples,
任务是生成示例，合成示例，
let's say an image,
比如一张照片，
in a single shot,
在一次中，
by taking some compressed or noisy latent space
通过获取一些压缩或噪声的潜在空间，
and then trying to decode or generate from that,
然后尝试从它解码或生成，
to produce now a new instance in our original data space.
在我们的原始数据空间中产生一个新的实例。
Diffusion models work fundamentally differently from this approach,
扩散模型的工作原理与这种方法截然不同，
rather than doing this one-shot prediction,
不是进行这种一次的预测，
what diffusion models do is that,
扩散模型所做的是，
they generate new samples iteratively,
它们迭代地产生新的样本，
by starting from purely random noise
从纯粹的随机噪声开始，
and learning a process
学习一个过程，
that can iteratively remove small increments of noise from that complete random state,
这个过程可以迭代地从完全随机状态中删除小增量的噪声，
all the way up back to being able to generate a synthetic example
直到能够生成合成示例，
in the original data landscape that we started off with and caring about.
在我们开始并关心的原始数据环境中。
The intuition here is really clever
这里的直觉真的很聪明，
and really, I think, powerful in that,
我认为，很强大，
what diffusion models allow us to do is
扩散模型使我们能够，
to capture maximum variability, maximum amount of information,
捕捉最大的可变性，最大的信息量，
by starting from a completely random state.
从一个完全随机的状态开始，
Diffusion models can be broken down into two key aspects,
扩散模型可以分为两个关键方面，
the first is what we call the forward noising process,
第一个是我们所说的前向噪声过程，
and at the core of this is
这个想法的核心是，
this idea of how we build up data, for the diffusion model to look at
我们如何建立数据，让扩散模型查看，
and then learn how to denoise and generate from.
然后学习如何去噪和生成数据。
The key step here is that we start with training data,
这里的关键一步是我们从训练数据开始，
let's say examples of images,
比如说图像的例子，
and over the course of this forward noising diffusion process,
在这个前向噪声扩散过程中，
what we do is we progressively add increasing increments of noise,
我们所做的是逐渐增加噪音，
such that we are slowly wiping out the details in the image,
这样我们就会慢慢地抹去图像中的细节，
corrupting the information, destroying that information,
破坏信息，摧毁信息，
until we arrive at a state that is pure noise.
直到我们达到纯粹的噪音状态。
Then, what we actually build our neural network to do is
然后，我们构建神经网络的目的是，
to learn a mapping that goes from that completely noise state back up to the original data space,
学习从完全噪声状态返回到原始数据空间的映射，
what we call the reverse process,
我们称之为反向过程，
learning and mapping that de noises,
学习和映射去噪声，
going from noise back up to data,
从噪声返回到数据，
and the core idea here is that,
这里的核心思想是，
denoising is iteratively recovering back more and more information from a completely random state.
去噪是从完全随机的状态迭代地恢复越来越多的信息。
These are the two core components,
这是两个核心部分，
the forward noising process, the reverse de noising process,
正向噪声过程和反向去噪过程，
and we're going to look at how each one works,
我们将看看每个过程是如何工作的，
distilled down to the core intuition.
归结为核心直觉。
Underlying this is the forward noising, the first step,
这下面是前向噪音，第一步，
where we're given an image
我们得到一幅图像，
and we want to arrive at a random sample of noise,
我们想要得到一个随机的噪声样本，
importantly, this process does not require any neural network learning, any training,
重要的是，这个过程不需要任何神经网络学习，任何训练，
what we are able to do is define a fixed way,
我们能够做的是定义一种固定的方式，
a determined way to go from that input image to the noise,
一种从输入图像到噪声的确定方式，
the core idea is really simple,
其核心理念非常简单，
all we do is we have some noising function,
我们所做的就是我们有一些噪音函数，
and starting at the first time step,
从第一个时间步长开始，
our initial time step T 0,
我们的初始时间步长 T0 ，
where we have 100% image, no noise added,
其中我们有 100% 的图像，没有添加任何噪声，
all we do is progressively add more and more noise in an iterative way,
我们所做的就是以迭代的方式逐渐增加越来越多的噪音，
over the course of these individual time steps,
在这些单独的时间步的过程中，
such that the result is increasingly more noisy.
以至于结果变得越来越嘈杂。
First, we go from all image, less image, less image,
首先，我们从所有图像开始，更少的图像，更少的图像，
more noise, more noise, all noise,
更多的噪音，更多的噪音，所有的噪音，
in this defined forward process,
在这个明确的前进过程中，
no training, no learning,
没有训练，没有学习，
all we have is a noising function.
我们所拥有的只是一个噪音函数。
Now, this gives us a bunch of examples, right,
现在，这给了我们很多例子，
if we have a bunch of instances instances in the dataset,
如果我们在数据集中有一堆实例，
we apply this noising to every one of them,
我们会将这种噪声应用于每个实例，
and so we have those slices at each of these different noising time steps,
所以我们在每个不同的噪声时间步长上都有这些切片，
our goal now in learning the neural network is
我们现在的目标是，学习神经网络，
to then learn how to denoising in this reverse process,
学习如何在这个相反的过程中去噪，
starting from data in the input space,
从输入空间中的数据开始，
what the noising process let us to is
噪声过程引导我们得到的是，
this time series of these iteratively, more noised examples.
这些迭代的、更有噪声的例子的时间序列。
Now our task is,
现在我们的任务是，
given an image,
给出一幅图像，
can we given a given one of these slices at these time steps, let's say T,
我们能不能在这些时间步长上，给出一个给定的切片，比如 T ，
all we're asking is,
我们所要问的是，
can we learn the next, next most denoise example from that time,
我们能不能知道从那个时间下一个去噪的例子，
making this more concrete, walk through it,
让它变得更具体，通过它，
a particular image at a slice, let's call it T,
一张切片上的图像，让我们称之为 T ，
what we ask the neural network to learn is
我们要求神经网络学习的是，
what is estimated image at that prior step T-1,
在前一步 T-1 的估计图像是什么，
making this very concrete,
让这个非常具体，
let's say we have this noised image at time 3,
让我们假设我们在时间 3 有这张有噪音的图像，
the neural network is then trying to predict,
然后，神经网络试图预测，
what was the denoise result at just one step before,
之前一个步骤的去噪结果是什么，
comparing these two,
将这两者进行比较，
let's take a step back,
让我们后退一步，
all these two images differ by is that noise function,
所有这两个图像的不同之处在于噪声函数，
and so the question that posed to the neural network in the course of training is,
所以，在训练过程中向神经网络提出的问题是，
how can we train, how can we learn this difference,
我们如何训练，我们如何才能学习这种区别，
if our goal is to learn this iterative denoising process,
如果我们的目标是学习这个迭代去噪过程，
and we have all these consecutive steps,
我们有所有这些连续的步骤，
going from more noise to less noise,
从更多的噪音到更少的噪音，
I pose a question to you all,
我向大家提出一个问题，
how could you think about,
你怎么能想到，
defining a loss, defining a training objective for the neural network to learn,
定义损失，定义神经网络要学习的训练目标，
any ideas?
有什么想法吗？
Yes.
好的。
Can you expand a little further on that?
你能在这一点上做进一步的阐述吗？
It gets, so the idea was,
它会，所以想法是，
can we look at the same concept
我们能不能看看同样的概念，
of trying to encode information from an image to maybe a reduced latent space
试图将图像中的信息编码到一个可能减少的潜在空间，
and try to learn that,
并试图学习它，
it's getting, it's getting, that's very related to what the network is actually doing,
它得到的与网络做的事情非常相关的东西，
but something even simpler,
但更简单的东西，
thinking about how can we just compare these two images?
想想我们如何才能只比较这两个图像？
Yes.
好的。
Simple, just think really simply.
很简单，只需要简单的思考。
Exactly,
没错，
the idea was how many of the pixels are the same,
想法是，有多少像素是相同的，
all we need to do, it turns out, is
事实证明，我们所需要做的就是，
look at the pixel wise difference between these two steps
看看这两个步骤之间的像素差异，
and the cleverness behind diffusion models is
而扩散模型背后的聪明就是，
defining that exact residual noise as what defines the loss.
定义这个残余噪声作为定义损耗。
The training objective for such a model,
对于这样一个模型的训练目标，
all you do is compare these consecutive time steps of iterative, iterative noising
你所要做的就是比较这些迭代噪声的连续时间步长，
and ask, what is that mean squared error,
然后问，均方误差是多少，
what is that pixel wise difference between those two.
这两者之间的像素差异是什么。
And it turns out that this works very effectively in practice,
事实证明，这在实践中非常有效，
that we can train a neural network to do this iterative denoising
我们可以训练神经网络进行迭代去噪，
by this very intuitive idea of the loss.
通过这种非常直观的损失概念。
All right, so hopefully this gives you the space
好的，希望这能给你提供空间，
of how the diffusion model builds up this understanding of the denoising process
说明扩散模型如何建立对去噪过程的理解，
and is able to go in learning to iteratively denoise examples.
并能够学习迭代地去噪例子。
Now the task is how can we actually sample something brand new,
现在的任务是我们如何才能取样全新的东西，
how can we generate a new instance.
我们如何生成一个新实例。
Well, it's very related to that exact reverse process,
这与那个完全相反的过程非常相关，
the denoising process that we just walked through,
我们刚刚经历的去噪过程，
what we do is
我们要做的是，
we take a brand new instance of completely random noise,
拿出一个全新的完全随机噪音的实例，
and take our trained diffusion model
然后用我们训练过的扩散模型，
and ask it, okay, just predict that residual noise difference,
来问它，好的，只需预测剩余噪声差，
that will get us to something that is slightly less noisy,
可以让我们得到噪音稍微小一些的东西，
and this is all that is done,
这就是它所做的，
repeatedly at these iterative time steps,
在这些迭代的时间步长上重复做的所有事情，
such that we can go from pure noise to something less noisy, repeatedly,
这样我们可以从纯粹的噪音到不那么嘈杂的东西，反复发生，
and as this process occurs,
随着这个过程的发生，
hopefully you can see the emergence of something that reflects image related content,
希望你能看到反映图像相关内容的东西的出现，
time step by time step, iteratively doing this sampling procedure,
时间一步一步，迭代地做这个采样程序，
over many generations and many time steps,
跨越了许多世代和许多时间步调，
such that we can get back to the point of this dog,
这样我们就可以回到这只狗，
that's peeking out through us.
正在看着我们。
What I want you to take away with is that,
我想让你们明白的是，
what the diffusion model enables is that,
扩散模型实现的是，
going from a completely random noise state,
从一个完全随机的噪声状态，
where we have this maximum notion of variability,
我们有最大的可变性概念，
by defining it and breaking it down to this iterative process,
通过定义它并将其分解为这个迭代过程，
at each of those steps there is a prediction that's made,
在每个步骤中都有一个做出的预测，
there is a generation that's made,
有一个世代做出，
and so that maximum variability is translated into maximum diversity in the generated samples.
所以最大的变异性转化为生成的样本中的最大多样性。
Such that, when we get to the end state,
这样，当我们到达最终状态时，
we have arrived at an image, a synthetic sample,
我们就得到了一幅图像，一个合成样本，
that's back in our completely noise free data space.
在完全没有噪音的数据空间中。
So at its core,
所以在它的核心，
this is the summary of how a diffusion model works
这是一个扩散模型如何工作的总结，
and how they're able to go from completely random noise
以及它们如何能够从完全随机的噪音
to very faithful, diverse, newly generated samples.
变成非常可靠的、多样化的、新产生的样本。
As I've kind of been alluding to,
正如我已经提到的，
what I think is so powerful about this approach and this idea
我认为这种方法的强大之处在于，
is the fact that we can start from complete randomness,
我们可以从完全随机开始，
it encapsulates maximum variability,
它封装了最大的可变性，
such that now diffusion models are able to produce generated samples that are very, very diverse,
因此现在扩散模型能够产生非常多样化的样本，
from noise samples, that are fundamentally different to each other,
来自彼此根本不同的噪声样本，
what this means is
这意味着，
now in this one instance,
现在在这个例子中，
we go from some noise sample to this image,
我们从一些噪声样本转到这张图像，
but equivalently and what is striking is,
但同样令人震惊的是，
if we consider now a completely different instance of random noise,
如果我们考虑一个完全不同的随机噪声实例，
they're very variable from each other, right,
他们彼此之间的差异很大，
random noise, random noise, maximum variability internally and in comparison to each other,
随机噪声、随机噪声，内部最大变异性和相互比较，
the result, as a result of that denoising generation is going to be a different sampled image,
去噪的结果将是一个不同的采样图像，
that's highly diverse, highly different to what we saw before.
它高度多样化，与我们以前看到的非常不同。
And that's really the power of diffusion models
这就是扩散模型的能力，
in thinking about how we can generate new samples that are very different and diverse.
在思考我们如何产生非常不同和多样化的新样本时。
Quick question, yes.
问题，好的。
Yep.
是的。
That's a fantastic question,
这是个很棒的问题，
so the question was,
所以问题是，
how does the model know when to stop,
模型如何知道何时停止，
when you build these models,
当你构建这些模型时，
you define a set number of time steps,
你定义了一组时间步长，
and this is a parameter,
这是一个参数，
that you can play around with when building and training the diffusion model,
你可以在构建和训练扩散模型时使用，
and there are different studies looking at what works and what doesn't work,
而且有不同的研究来观察什么有效，什么无效，
the core idea is,
核心思想是，
by more time steps,
通过更多的时间步长，
you're going to result in better resolution effectively of generations,
你将产生更好的世代清晰度，
but it's a trade off as well
但这也是一种权衡，
in terms of the stability of the model and how efficiently it can train and learn.
就模型的稳定性以及培训和学习的效率而言。
So, so the question was,
所以，所以问题是，
if, explaining why there could be some missing details or incorrect details in the results of the diffusion models
解释为什么扩散模型的结果中可能会有一些遗漏的细节或不正确的细节，
and the particular example was [hands] in particular.
特别是手的例子。
I don't know if there is a specific reason for why hands seem to cause issues,
我不知道为什么手似乎会引起问题，
I personally haven't seen reports or examples or literature discussing that,
我个人还没有看到讨论这一问题的报告、例子或文献，
but I think, the, the general point is,
但我认为，大体上是，
yes, there is, there are going to be imperfections, right,
是的，会有不完美的地方，
it's not going to be 100% perfect or accurate
它不会是 100% 完美或准确，
in terms of faithfulness to the, to the true example,
在对真实的实例的可能方面，
and I think a lot of advances are now,
我认为现在的许多进展，
like thinking about what are modifications to the underlying architecture,
比如思考对底层体系结构进行哪些修改，
that could try to alleviate some of those details or those issues,
可以尝试缓解其中的一些细节或问题，
but for the sake of lecture,
但为了讲课，
I can discuss further with you about that particular example afterwards as well.
我也可以在后面进一步讨论这个特定的例子。
Okay.
好的。
So.
所以。
So, so, yeah, indeed, I think the power and the power of these models is, is very, very significant
所以，是的，确实，我认为这些模型的力量是非常非常重要的，
and going back to the example that we showed at lecture one, right,
回到我们在第一节课上展示的例子，
this ability to generate now a synthetic image
这种能力现在可以生成一个合成图像，
from a language prompt photo of an astronaut riding a horse.
从”一张宇航员骑马的照片“的语言提示。
In fact, it is a diffusion model that is underlying this this approach,
事实上，这种方法的基础是一个扩散模型，
and what the diffusion model is doing is,
而扩散模型所做的是，
it's able to take an embedding that translates between text and language
它能够在文本和语言之间进行转换，
and then run a diffusion process between the two,
然后在两者之间运行扩散过程，
such that image generation can be guided by the particular language prompt.
这样图像生成就可以由特定的语言提示来引导。
More examples of this idea of text to image generation have, I think,
我认为，更多这种从文本到图像生成的想法
really taken the Internet kind of by storm,
已经在互联网上掀起了一场风暴，
but I think what is so powerful about this idea is that,
但我认为这个想法的强大之处在于，
we can guide the generative process according to constraints that we specify through language,
我们可以根据我们通过语言指定的约束来指导生成过程，
which is very, very powerful,
这是非常非常强大的，
everything from something that's highly photo realistic
所有的东西都是高度照片逼真的，
or generated with a specific art, artistic style,
或者是用特定的艺术、艺术风格产生的，
as in the examples that I'm showing here.
就像我在这里展示的例子一样。
So, so far,
所以，到目前为止，
in both today's portion on diffusion models and our discussion of generative models more broadly,
在今天关于扩散模型的部分和我们对生成模型的更广泛的讨论中，
we largely focused on examples in images,
我们主要集中在图像中的例子，
but what about other data modalities, other applications,
但是，其他数据形态、其他应用程序呢，
can we design new generative models,
我们能设计出新的生成式模型吗，
leveraging these ideas to design new synthetic instances in other real world application areas.
利用这些想法在其他现实世界应用领域中设计新的合成实例。
To me, and I'm definitely biased in saying this,
对我来说，我这样说肯定是有偏见的，
but one of the most exciting aspects about thinking about this idea is,
但思考这个想法最令人兴奋的方面之一是，
in the context of molecular design
在分子设计的背景下，
and how it can relate to chemistry, the life sciences and environmental science as well.
以及它如何与化学、生命科学和环境科学相关联。
So for example, in the, in the landscape of chemistry and small molecules,
例如，在化学和小分子领域，
now instead of thinking about images and pixels,
现在不是考虑图像和像素，
we can think about atoms and molecules in 3D space.
我们考虑三维空间中的原子和分子。
And there's been a lot of recent work in building now diffusion models,
最近在建立扩散模型方面已经做了很多工作，
that can look at the 3D coordinates of atoms defining a molecule
可以观察定义分子的原子的三维坐标，
and go from a completely random state in that 3D space
从三维空间中的完全随机状态
to again perform this same iterative denoising procedure
到再次执行同样的迭代去噪过程，
to now generate molecular structures that are well defined
现在生成定义良好的分子结构，
and could be used for applications in drug discovery or therapeutic design.
可以用于药物发现或治疗设计。
Beyond that, and in my research specifically,
除此之外，特别是在我的研究中，
we are building new diffusion models,
我们正在建立新的扩散模型，
that can generate biological molecules or biological sequences, like those of proteins,
可以产生生物分子或生物序列，比如蛋白质，
which are the actuators and executors of all of biological function in human life
它们是人类生活中所有生物功能的执行者和执行者，
and across all the domains of life.
跨越生命的所有领域。
And specifically, in my work and in my research team,
具体地说，在我的工作和我的研究团队中，
we've developed a new diffusion model,
我们开发了一种新的扩散模型，
that is capable of generating brand new protein structures,
它能够产生全新的蛋白质结构，
I'm going to share a little bit about how that model works
我将分享一点关于这个模式的工作原理
and our core idea behind it
和在它后面的我们的核心理念，
to kind of close out this section.
来结束这一部分。
The motivation that is really driving this work across the field at large is
真正推动整个领域这项工作的动机是，
this goal of trying to design new biological entities, like proteins,
这个试图设计新的生物实体的目标，比如蛋白质，
that could have therapeutic functions or expand the functional space of biology at large.
可以具有治疗功能或者扩大生物学的功能空间。
And there are many, many efforts across generative AI,
在生成式 AI 领域有很多努力，
that are now aiming at this problem,
现在都在针对这个问题，
because of the tremendous potential impact that it can have.
因为它可能会产生巨大的潜在影响。
So in our work in specific,
在我们的具体工作中，
we considered this problem of protein design
我们考虑蛋白质设计这个问题，
by going back to the biology and drawing inspiration from it,
通过回到生物学并从中获得灵感，
and if you consider how protein function is determined and encoded,
如果你考虑蛋白质功能是如何决定和编码的，
all it is distilled down to is the structure of that protein in 3D space,
它被浓缩成，蛋白质结构在三维空间中，
and how that structure informs and encodes a particular biological function,
这种结构如何告知和编码特定的生物功能，
in turn, proteins don't always start out adopting a particular 3D structure,
反过来，蛋白质并不总是一开始就采用特定的三维结构，
they go through this process of what we call protein folding,
它们经历了我们所称的蛋白质折叠的过程，
that defines how the chain of atoms in the protein wiggle around in 3D space
这定义了蛋白质中的原子链如何在三维空间中摆动，
to adopt a final defined 3D structure,
以采用最终定义的三维结构，
that is highly specific and highly linked to a particular biological function.
该结构高度特定，并与特定的生物功能高度相关。
So we asked, and we looked at this question of protein folding
所以我们问，我们研究了蛋白质折叠的问题，
and how protein folding leads to structure
以及蛋白质折叠是如何导致结构的，
to inspire a new diffusion model approach for this protein structured design problem.
以启发一种新的扩散模型方法来解决这个蛋白质结构设计问题。
Where we said, okay,
我们说，好的，
if a protein is in a completely unfolded state,
如果蛋白质处于完全未折叠的状态，
you can think about that as equivalent to the random noise state in an image,
你可以认为这等同于图像中的随机噪声状态，
it's in a completely floppy configuration,
它完全是松松垮垮的配置，
it doesn't have a defined structure, it's unfolded.
它没有明确的结构，它是展开的。
And what we did is,
我们所做的是，
we took that notion of protein protein structure being unfolded as the noisy state for a diffusion model,
把蛋白质结构被展开的概念作为扩散模型的噪声状态，
and we designed a diffusion model,
我们设计了一个扩散模型，
that we trained to go from that unfolded state of the protein
我们训练它从蛋白质的展开状态出发，
to then produce a generated prediction about a new structure,
然后产生一个关于新结构的预测，
that would define a specific 3D structure.
它将定义一个特定的三维结构。
And we can visualize how this algorithm works
我们可以直观地看到这个算法是如何工作的，
and we call it folding diffusion,
我们称之为折叠扩散，
in this video, that I'm going to show here,
在这段视频中，我将在这里展示，
where at the start in this initial frame,
在开始的初始帧中，
we have a random noise protein chain,
我们有一个随机的噪音蛋白质链，
completely random configuration unfolded and unfolded in 3D space,
完全随机的配置在 3D 空间中展开，
now, what it's going to show this video is the iterative denoising steps,
现在，这段视频将展示的是去噪步骤，
that go from that noise random state to the final generated structure.
从随机噪因状态到最终生成的结构。
And as you can see,
正如你所看到的，
it's this process very similar to the concept that I introduce with images,
这个过程非常类似于我用图像介绍的概念，
where we're trying to go from something noisy to something structured,
我们试图从嘈杂的东西变成有结构的东西，
arriving now at a final generated protein structure.
现在到达最终生成的蛋白质结构。
So our work was really focused on
所以，我们的工作实际上集中在，
introducing a new and foundational algorithm for this protein structured design problem,
为蛋白质结构设计问题引入一种新的基础性算法，
via this, via diffusion models.
通过扩散模型。
But it turns out that,
但事实证明，
in just a very short time from when we and others introduced these algorithms,
在我们和其他人引入这些算法后的很短时间内，
that it precipitated really arise in scaling and extending these diffusion models
在缩放和扩展这些扩散模型出现了沉淀，
for very, very specific controlled programmable protein design,
以进行非常具体的可编程蛋白质设计时，
where now we are seeing large scale efforts,
现在我们看到了大规模的努力，
that use these diffusion model algorithms to generate protein designs
使用这些扩散模型算法来产生蛋白质设计，
and actually realize them experimentally in the physical world.
并在物理世界中实际实验实现它们。
So in this image I'm showing on the left,
所以在这张我在左边展示的图像中，
the colored image is the generated output by the diffusion model,
彩色图像是扩散模型生成的输出，
and the black and white image is what,
黑白图像是，
if you take that result, synthesize it in the biological lab
如果你得到这个结果，在生物实验室里合成它，
and look and take a picture of the resulting protein
然后看着并拍下产生的蛋白质的照片，
and assess its structure,
然后评估它的结构，
we see that there is a strong correspondence,
我们看到有很强的一致性，
meaning that we're at the ability to leverage these powerful diffusion models
这意味着我们有能力利用这些强大的扩散模型
to now generate new proteins,
来产生新的蛋白质，
that can be realized in the physical world.
这些蛋白质可以在物理世界中实现。
It doesn't stop there,
这并不止步于此，
we can now think about designing proteins for very specific therapeutic applications,
我们现在可以考虑为非常具体的治疗应用设计蛋白质，
so for example, in this visualization,
例如，在这个可视化中，
this is designed as a novel protein binder,
这被设计成一种新型蛋白质结合剂，
that's designed to block, to bind to and block the activity of the COVID spike receptor.
旨在结合和阻止 COVID spike 受体的活动。
So what you're seeing, again, is that,
所以你再一次看到的是，
visualization of the diffusion process in arriving at a final design,
在最终的设计中，扩散过程的可视化，
that binds to and blocks the top of the covid spike receptor.
结合并阻止了 COVID spike 受体的顶部。
So hopefully, you know, this kind of paints
所以，希望，这种方式描绘了
a bit of the landscape of where we are today with generative AI,
我们今天所处的生成式 AI 的全景，
and I think that this example in in protein science and in biology more broadly
我认为在蛋白质科学和更广泛的生物学的例子中，
really highlights the fact,
突出了这样一个事实，
that generative AI is now at the ability to enable truly impactful applications,
生成式 AI 现在能够实现真正有影响力的应用程序，
not just for creating cool images
不仅仅是为了创造很酷的图像，
or what we can think of as AI synthetic art,
或者我们可以认为是人工智能合成艺术，
generative AI is now enabling us to think about design solutions for real world problems.
生成式 AI 现在使我们能够思考现实世界问题的设计解决方案。
And I think there are so many open questions
我认为，还有很多悬而未决问题，
in understanding the capabilities, the limitations, the applications of generative AI approaches
在理解生成式 AI 方法的能力、局限性、应用上，
and how they can empower our society.
以及它们如何增强我们的社会能力方面。
So to conclude, I want to end on a higher level thought.
作为总结，我想以一个更高层次的思考来结束。
And that's the fact that this idea of generative design kind of raises this higher level concept
这就是，这种生成性设计的想法提升了这个更高层次的概念，
of what it means to understand,
关于理解意味着什么，
and I think it's captured perfectly in this quote by the physicist Richard Feynman,
我认为物理学家 Richard Feynman 的这句话完美地捕捉到了这一点，
who said what I cannot create, I cannot understand,
他说，我无法创造的东西，我无法理解，
in order to create something,
为了创造一些东西，
we as humans really have to understand how it works,
作为人类，我们真的必须了解它是如何工作的，
and conversely, in order to understand something fully,
相反，为了完全理解一些东西，
I'd argue that we'd have to create it engineer design,
我认为我们必须创造出工程设计，
generative AI and generative intelligence is at the core of this idea
生成式 AI 和生成性智能是这个概念的核心，
of what I think about as concept learning,
我所认为的概念学习，
being able to, distill a very complex problem down to its core roots,
能够提炼出一个非常复杂的问题的核心根源，
and then build up from that foundation to design and to create,
然后在这个基础上发展到设计和创造，
when this course began on Monday,
当这门课程在周一开始时，
Alexander introduced the idea of what it means to be intelligent,
Alexander 介绍了什么智能的概念，
loosely speaking, right, the ability to take information, use it to inform a future decision,
通俗地说，是指能够获取信息，并将其用于未来决策的能力，
human learning is not only restricted to the ability to solve specific, distinct tasks,
人类的学习不仅限于解决具体、不同任务的能力，
it's foundational and founded by the idea of being able to understand concepts
它是建立在能够理解概念的想法上，
and using those concepts to be creative, to imagine, to inspire, to dream,
并使用这些概念来创造、想象、启发和梦想，
I think now we're at the point where we have to really think about
我认为，现在我们必须真正思考，
what this notion of intelligence really means,
智能这个概念的真正含义，
and how it relates to the connections and distinctions
以及它的联系和区别，
between artificial intelligence and what we as humans can do and create.
在人工智能和我们作为人类能够做和创造的东西之间。
So with that, I'm going to leave you with that,
说到这里，我就把这个留给你们，
and I hope that inspires you to think further
我希望这能启发你们进一步思考，
on what we've talked about in the course
我们在课程中谈到的内容，
and intelligence, AI, deep learning, more broadly.
以及更广泛的智能，人工智能，深度学习。
So thank you very much for your attention,
所以，非常感谢你的关注，
we're going to take a very brief pause,
我们要稍作停顿，
since we're, I know we're running a little bit late
因为我们有点晚了，
and then have our fantastic lecture from Ramin.
然后由 Ramin 开始我们精彩的演讲。
Thank you so much.
非常感谢。